Ren d'Harnoncourt Papers
The Museum of Modern Art, Publisher
- Series VI: MoMA International Council, 1952-1967
  This series contains records of the Museums International Council, which was established in 1953 under d'Harnoncourt's guidance. Included in the records are minutes of meetings, and correspondence about many of the international exhibitions, which were organized during d'Harnoncourt's years as MoMAs director. These include the Venice Biennales and the So Paulo Bienals.
  - Venice Biennale, 1966-68; Correspondence. (Folder VI.1)
  - Venice Biennale, 1962; Correspondence about the 1962 Venice Biennale at which the American exhibition was organized by MoMA. (Folder VI.2)
  - Venice Biennale, 1962; Correspondence about the 1962 Venice Biennale at which the American exhibition was organized by MoMA. (Folder VI.3)
  - Venice Biennale, 1957-58; Correspondence about the 1958 Venice Biennale at which the American exhibition was organized by MoMA. (Folder VI.4)
  - Venice Biennale, 1955-57; Correspondence about the 1956 Venice Biennale at which the American exhibition was organized by the Art Institute of Chicago at MoMAs invitation. (Folder VI.5)
  - Venice Biennale, 1953-54; Correspondence about the 1954 Venice Biennale at which the American exhibition was organized by MoMA. Also correspondence about the 1954 purchase by the Museum of the American pavilion in Venice from the Grand Central Art Galleries. (Folder VI.6)
  - Venice Biennale and So Paulo Bienal, 1950-60; Lists of American exhibitions held at the Venice Biennale and the So Paulo Bienal 1950-60. (Folder VI.7)
  - So Paulo Bienal, 1960-63; Correspondence about the 1961 So Paulo Bienal at which the U.S. exhibition was organized by MoMA. (Folder VI.8)
  - So Paulo Bienal, 1956-59; Correspondence about the 1957 So Paulo Bienal at which the U.S. exhibition was organized by MoMA, and the 1959 Bienal which was organized by the Minneapolis Institute of Arts at MoMAs invitation. (Folder VI.9)
  - So Paulo Bienal, 1955-56; Correspondence about the 1955 So Paulo Bienal at which the U.S. exhibition was organized by the San Francisco Museum of Art (with the collaboration of the Los Angeles County Museum) at MoMAs invitation. (Folder VI.10)
  - So Paulo Bienal, 1953-54; Correspondence about the 1953-54 So Paulo Bienal at which the U.S. exhibition was organized by MoMA. (Folder VI.11)
  - So Paulo Bienal, 1953-54; Photographs, plans for assembling Calder works for the exhibition. (Folder VI.12)
  - Mark Rothko Exhibition, 1962-65; Correspondence about the Rothko exhibition held in Paris, 12/62. (Folder VI.13)
  - Latin American Program, 1965-67; Correspondence. (Folder VI.14)
  - International Council - General 1965-67, Correspondence, minutes of meetings, lists of exhibitions being sponsored by the Council. (Folder VI.15)
  - Muse Rodin (Paris) American Sculpture Exhibition - Summer 1965, 1964-66; Correspondence about the exhibition,Modern Sculpture: U.S.A., sponsored by the International Council of MoMA, held at the Muse Rodin, Paris, 6/22-10/10/65. Correspondents include RDH, Madame Cecile Goldscheider, conservateur of the Muse Rodin, Mrs. Bliss Parkinson, president of the International Council, Waldo Rasmussen, Frank OHara, and Alicia Legg. 1 TLS Dimitri Hadzi - RDH (3/1/65) discussing his work, and asking which should be used in the exhibition. (Folder VI.16)
  - David Smith Exhibition, 1965-67; Correspondence. (Folder VI.17)
  - Art Israel Exhibition, 1964-66; Correspondence. (Folder VI.18)
  - Overseas Library Committee, 1965-67; Correspondence about the International Councils Library Overseas Program. (Folder VI.19)
  - American Sculpture Exhibition, 1965-66; Correspondence about showings of the exhibition Modern Sculpture: U.S.A. in other European cities after it closed in Paris. (Folder VI.20)
  - Art in Embassies Project, 1964-67; Correspondence, minutes of meetings, lists of works of art loaned to U.S. embassies throughout the world. (Folder VI.21)
  - Art in Embassies Project, 1961; Correspondence between RDH and Robert H. Thayer, Special Assistant to the Secretary of State, about a report that Mr. Thayer was preparing for the Secretary of State about problems related to installing American art in embassies abroad. (Folder VI.22)
  - Murrow correspondence, 1962-63; Brief correspondence with Edward R. Murrow, Director, U.S. Information Agency. (Folder VI.23)
  - Tax Bill - 1964, Correspondence about the Revenue Act of 1964. (Folder VI.24)
  - Loans to Secretary of State Rusk, 1961-62; Inter-office correspondence about Secretary of State Dean Rusks request for pictures for his office and reception rooms. (Folder VI.25)
  - White House Conference on International Cooperation Nov. 28 - Dec. 1, 1965, 1965-66; Correspondence and programs. 1 TLS Vice President Hubert H. Humphrey - RDH (1/4/66) thanking RDH for his help and for contributing to the success of the White House Conference. Address by Dr. Frank Stanton to the Panel on Cultural and Intellectual Exchange (12/1/65). (Folder VI.26)
  - Pan American Building, 1961; Brief correspondence about a meeting to be attended by Walter Gropius, Richard Lippold, Pietro Belluschi, RDH, and Juan Trippe to discuss the sculpture by Lippold to be installed in the Pan Am Building. 1 TLS Walter Gropius - RDH (2/16/61) telling RDH about the forthcoming meeting. (Folder VI.27)
  - Goldberg Correspondence, 1961-64; RDH correspondence with Arthur J. Goldberg, Secretary of Labor, later Supreme Court Justice, and with his wife. The correspondence is about Secretary Goldbergs request for paintings for his office, and later about a statement made by him on the state of the performing arts. (Folder VI.28)
  - Kennedy Correspondence, 1962-63; Correspondence with Mrs. John F. Kennedy and her social secretary, Letitia Baldrige, about Mrs. Kennedy agreeing to become an Honorary Member of the International Council. Correspondence also about Mrs. Kennedy agreeing to present a portfolio on the Childrens Art Carnival - which the Council and The Asia Society were donating to the National Childrens Museum of New Delhi - to Mrs. Indira Gandhi while on her trip to India. Copy letter RDH - Mrs. John F. Kennedy (1/29/62) asking her to become an Honorary Member of the Council. Copy letter Mrs. John F. Kennedy - RDH (2/5/62) accepting the invitation. (Folder VI.29)
  - Inter-American Foundation for the Arts, 1965-66; Correspondence. (Folder VI.30)
  - International Cooperation Year - 1965, Correspondence and copy of the report of the Committee on Painting, Sculpture, and the Crafts. (Folder VI.31)
  - The White House Festival of the Arts - June 14, 1965, Program of the days events. Correspondence about the works lent by MoMA to the White House for the Festival. (Folder VI.32)
  - Inter-American Foundation for the Arts, 1963-65; Correspondence, reports. (Folder VI.33)
  - La Cit Internationale des Arts, Paris, 1962-65; Correspondence and brochures about the Cit Internationale des Arts in Paris and the American Center for Students and Artists which became affiliated with it - offering ateliers and studios for painters, sculptors, musicians, etc. (Folder VI.34)
  - Department of State, 1962-63; State Department press releases on cultural exchange. (Folder VI.35)
  - American Iron and Steel Institute Sculpture Competition, 1964-65; Correspondence about the sculpture competition organized by the steel industry to commemorate the second century of steel making in the United States. Welcoming remarks by RDH at the ceremony at MoMA when the award winning sculpture by Jos de Rivera was presented to the Museum by the American Iron and Steel Institute. (11/10/65). Press release (11/10/65) gives details of the competition. (Folder VI.36)
  - William Zorach Fountain, 1960; Correspondence about the gift of a fountain to the City of Bath, Maine, by William Zorach. (Folder VI.37)
  - Freedom from Hunger Campaign, 1964; Brief correspondence about possibility of a Freedom from Hunger exhibition similar to the Museums Family of Man exhibition. Printed material. (Folder VI.38)
  - Look Magazine Article on Indian Art, 1963; Text of a brief article on Indian Art and the photographs which accompanied it in Look magazine. RDH is mentioned in the article and helped in its preparation. (Folder VI.39)
  - Postal Rates, 1961; Correspondence about proposed postal rate increases. (Folder VI.40)
  - Equitable Life Assurance Society, 1961-62; 1965; Correspondence. (Folder VI.41)
  - Department of State - Educational and Cultural Affairs, 1962; RDH correspondence with Max Isenbergh, about the possibility of government support for the Venice Biennale, and with Mr. Isenbergh and Lucius Battle about the selection of pictures from the Downtown Gallery to be loaned to the Bureau of Educational and Cultural Affairs. (Folder VI.42)
  - The School of Paris Exhibition, 1964-66; Correspondence about the exhibition The School of Paris: Paintings from the FloRen May Schoenborn & Samuel A. Marx Collection which, following its showing in New York, went to Chicago, St. Louis, Mexico City, and San Francisco. (Folder VI.43)
  - The School of Paris Exhibition, 1966; Photographs and newspaper clippings of the opening of the exhibition The School of Paris at the Museo de Arte Moderno, Mexico City, 7/2/66, which was attended by RDH and other members of the International Council. (Folder VI.44)
  - Japanese Show, 1961-64; Voluminous correspondence about the possibility of an exhibition of Japanese art at MoMA, and an exhibition of American art in Japan. Correspondents include Waldo Rasmussen, RDH, William S. Lieberman, and Porter McCray. Reports on the second United States-Japan Conference on Cultural and Educational Interchange, 10/16-22/63. (Folder VI.45)
  - International Circulating Exhibitions, 1954-55; Correspondence. 1 TLS MW - RDH (3/1/54) reporting on his trip to India. (Folder VI.46)
  - Orangerie Exhibition, 1954; Correspondence, summary of first meeting of selection committee for exhibition of 19th century French paintings in U.S. collections to be held in the Orangerie, Paris, in early 1955 (11/23/54). The exhibition was shown under the title De David a Toulouse-Lautrec, 4/21-7/3/55. 1 copy letter President Eisenhower - William Burden (11/8/54) saying how important he thought the 19th century French paintings exhibition would be for French/American friendship - it was requested by the French Ministry of Foreign Affairs - and also saying how pleased he was that at Ambassador Douglas Dillons request Mr. Burden had agreed to serve as chairman of a committee to organize the exhibition. (Folder VI.47)
  - Orangerie Exhibition, 1954; Correspondence. (Folder VI.48)
  - Orangerie Exhibition, 1955; Extensive correspondence, press release giving names of exhibition committee members and other details about the exhibition (1/19/55). (Folder VI.49)
  - Orangerie Exhibition, 1955; Correspondence. (Folder VI.50)
  - Belgrade Exhibition, 1956; Correspondence about the International Programs exhibition Modern Art in the United States held in Belgrade (7/6-8/6/56). (Folder VI.51)
  - Proposed American Indian Exhibition in Europe, 1955-56; Correspondence. (Folder VI.52)
  - Avalon Foundation - International Program, 1958; Correspondence and material relating to a request for a grant from the Avalon Foundation. (Folder VI.53)
  - Barcelona Exhibition, 1955-56; Correspondence about an exhibition,Modern Art in the United States - Selections from the Collections of The Museum of Modern Art presented at the III Bienal Hispanoamericana de Arte, Barcelona 9/24-10/24/55. (Folder VI.54)
  - Design Show in India, 1956-59; Correspondence about the design exhibition in India, and about American participation in the 3rd International Contemporary Art Exhibition, sponsored by the All-India Fine Arts Society, which was organized by MoMA. (Folder VI.55)
  - The Hague Exhibition, 1956; Copy of foreword to catalogue of exhibition,Modern Art in the United States: Selections from the Collections of The Museum of Modern Art, by RDH. Copy letter Porter McCray - Earle Balch, Cultural Affairs Officer, USIS, (3/7/56) about press reaction to the opening of the exhibition. (Folder VI.56)
  - Industrial Design Show - Japan, 1956-58; Correspondence about the exhibition 20th Century Design in Europe and America: Selections from the Collection of The Museum of Modern Art, New York, held in Japan in early 1957. (Folder VI.57)
  - Italian Art, 1958-59; Brief correspondence and project proposal for an exhibition of 20th century art from American collections. (Folder VI.58)
  - Watercolor Show - France, 1956; Correspondence about an exhibition,Recent American Watercolors, shown in Paris and other French cities. (Folder VI.59)
  - International Council - Ad Hoc Committee, 1956; Correspondence and minutes of meetings. (Folder VI.60)
  - Frankfurt Exhibition, 1955-56; Correspondence about the exhibition Modern Art in the United States: Selections from the Collections of The Museum of Modern Art, New York, held in Frankfurt. Draft of the remarks made by NAR at the opening of the exhibition (11/12/55). Draft of the foreword to the exhibition catalogue by RDH. (Folder VI.61)
  - Munch Exhibition, 1956-57; Correspondence about the exhibition at MoMA of graphic work by Edvard Munch on loan from Oslo. (2/5/-3/3/57). (Folder VI.62)
  - American Room, UNESCO headquarters, Paris, 1958; Correspondence about the painting to be hung in the UNESCO building, Paris. 1 TLS Christian Herter, Under Secretary, Department of State - Mr. and Mrs. d'Harnoncourt (7/18/58) inviting them and members of the International Council to the opening of the new Paris headquarters of UNESCO (11/3/58), and thanking them for their part in making possible the decoration of the American Room. (Folder VI.63)
  - Latin American Architecture Exhibition, Panama, 1958; Correspondence about the proposed showing of the exhibition Latin American Architecture Since 1945 in Panama. (Folder VI.64)
  - Madrid Exhibition, 1958-59; Correspondence about the exhibition The New American Painting shown at the Museo de Arte Contemporaneo, Madrid (7/16-8/15/58), and about RDHs visit to Madrid for the exhibition opening. (Folder VI.65)
  - Tate Gallery, 1955-57; Correspondence about the exhibition Modern Art in the United States: Selection from the Collections of The Museum of Modern Art shown at the Tate Gallery. (Folder VI.66)
  - Muse Rodin, 1955-56; Correspondence about American participation in an international sculpture exhibition to be shown in the garden of the Muse Rodin. (Folder VI.67)
  - Vienna Exhibition, 1956; Correspondence about the exhibition Modern Art in the United States shown at the Vienna Secession. RDH gave an introductory lecture on the exhibition in German (5/10/56). (Folder VI.68)
  - Zurich Exhibition, 1955; Correspondence about the exhibition Modern Art in the United States shown in Zurich. (Folder VI.69)
  - International Council Brochure, 1956-57; Drafts of International Council brochure. (Folder VI.70)
  - MoMA International Activities, 1952-56; Report on International Activities of The Museum of Modern Art, 1952-56. (Folder VI.71)
  - International Council of The Museum of Modern Art 1953-54, Minutes of meetings, interoffice correspondence about the formation of the International Council. Minutes of the meeting of the committee for the formation of the International Council (10/21/53), at which Mrs. John D. Rockefeller, 3rd, chairman, reported that the International Council was approved by the Board of Trustees at their meeting (10/8/53). By-laws of the Council, and Introductory Statement about it. (Folder VI.72)
  - Family of Man Exhibition in Moscow, 1958-59; Correspondence. (Folder VI.73)
  - Brussels Universal & International Exhibition, 1958 (Worlds Fair), 1957-58; Correspondence, minutes of meetings of Fine Arts Advisory Committee to the U.S. Commission for the Brussels Universal & International Exhibition, 1958. (Folder VI.74)
  - Brussels Universal & International Exhibition, 1958 (Worlds Fair), Press release from the office of the United States Commissioner General to the Brussels Worlds Fair - 1958 (1/22/58). Blueprints and plans of the U.S. Pavilion at the Fair. (Folder VI.75)
  - Program Committee Meeting, 1957-58; Agenda, project proposals for the Program Committee meeting (5/19/58). (Folder VI.76)
  - International Council - General, 1958; Correspondence. (Folder VI.77)
  - International Council - General, 1957; Correspondence, press releases. (Folder VI.78)
  - International Council - General, 1956; Correspondence, minutes of meetings. (Folder VI.79)
  - International Council - General, 1955; Correspondence, minutes of meetings. (Folder VI.80)
  - French Drawing Exhibition, 1958-61; Correspondence about the exhibition French Drawings from American Collections shown at the Boymans Museum, Rotterdam (7/30/58-9/28/58) and the Orangerie, Paris (10/24/58-1/2/59). (Folder VI.81)
  - Muse National dArt Moderne, Paris, 1954-55; Correspondence about the exhibition American Art of the Twentieth Century, shown at the Muse National dArt Moderne as part of the Salut a la France (4/2/55-5/15/55). (Folder VI.82)
  - Muse National dArt Moderne, Paris, 1955; Correspondence about the exhibition American Art of the Twentieth Century, information (in French) about Salut a la France and MoMA, and a motion picture scenario of Salut a la France. (Folder VI.83)
  - Proposed Exhibition at the Grand Palais, Paris, 1954-58; Correspondence about a proposed exhibition on building techniques to be held at the Grand Palais, Paris. (Folder VI.84)
  - Committee for International Cultural Exchange, 1960-61; Correspondence, reports. (Folder VI.85)
  - Biennale de Paris 1963, 1961-63; Correspondence about the 3rd Paris Biennale, which RDH participated in. (Folder VI.86)
  - Biennale de Paris 1959, Correspondence about the 1st Paris Biennale. (Folder VI.87)
  - International Council - General, 1965-68; Correspondence. (Folder VI.88)
  - International Study Center, 1968; Contribution by the Joseph G. Mayer Foundation to the Lillie P. Bliss International Study Center. (Folder VI.89)
  - International Program, 1958-59; Correspondence. (Folder VI.90)
  - International Council - General, 1958-59; Correspondence, minutes of meetings, reports. (Folder VI.91)
  - International Program - Pollack (sic) Paintings, 1958-59; Correspondence about disputed ownership of two paintings by Jackson Pollock. Survey of press reaction to the exhibition Jackson Pollock: 1912-1956 shown at the 4th So Paulo Bienal and on tour to several cities in Europe. (Folder VI.92)
  - International Council - General, 1960-61; Correspondence, minutes of meetings, reports. (Folder VI.93)
  - International Council - General, 1961-64; Correspondence, minutes of meetings, reports. (Folder VI.94)
  - Battersea Park Project, 1962-63; Correspondence about the exhibition of American sculpture in Battersea Park, London, in summer 1963. (Folder VI.95)
  - Latin American Program, 1962-64; Correspondence. (Folder VI.96)
  - Art in Embassies Project, 1958-64; Correspondence, minutes of meetings. (Folder VI.97)
  - Art in Embassies Project, 1961-62; Correspondence, minutes of meetings. Article on the Art in Embassies project by Helen Franc published in Overseas, The Magazine of Educational Exchange, 11/62. (Folder VI.98)
  - Art in Embassies Project, 1961; Minutes of meetings, list of works of art loaned to American embassies throughout the world. (Folder VI.99)
  - International Program, 1954-55; Correspondence, informal review of the activities of the International Program, 10/54-11/55. (Folder VI.100)
  - International Council Symposium, May 1955, Correspondence about the symposium held at the end of the International Councils first annual conference, 5/12/55. Copy of the proceedings of the symposium including addresses by George Kennan, Aline Saarinen, and Ahmed Bokhari. (Folder VI.101)
  - International Program - Office Space, 1959; Memos from Porter McCray to RDH about office space needed for his staff. (Folder VI.102)
  - International Program, 1957-61; Lists of international circulating exhibitions, 1957-61. (Folder VI.103)
  - International Council - General, 1960-64; Correspondence, minutes of meetings, list of circulating exhibitions, 1963-64. (Folder VI.104)
  - International Council - General, 1964; Correspondence, minutes of the Council 8th annual meeting, 11/10-11/11/64, and report on meeting of the Council Program Committee, 10/22/64. (Folder VI.105)
  - International Council - General, 1963; Correspondence. (Folder VI.106)
  - International Council - General, 1963; Correspondence, minutes of spring meeting, Houston, 5/3-5/4/63. (Folder VI.107)
  - International Council - General, 1963; Minutes of meetings. (Folder VI.108)
  - International Council - General, 1961-63; Correspondence, minutes of meetings. (Folder VI.109)
  - International Council - General, 1962; Correspondence, minutes of meetings. (Folder VI.110)
  - International Council - General, 1962; Minutes of the spring meeting, 5/1/62. List of international circulating exhibitions. (Folder VI.111)
  - International Council - General, 1961; Correspondence, minutes of meetings. (Folder VI.112)
  - International Council - General, 1960-61; Correspondence, minutes of meetings. (Folder VI.113)
  - International Council - General, 1960-61; Correspondence, copy of Council by-laws and proposed amendments to the by-laws, press releases. (Folder VI.114)
  - International Council - General, 1965; Correspondence, minutes of spring meeting, 4/29/65. (Folder VI.115)
  - International Council - General, 1967; Minutes of meetings. (Folder VI.116)
- Series VII.: Correspondence with outside organizations, 1940s-1968
  This series encompasses Ren d'Harnoncourt's correspondence with outside organizations, both in his capacity as Director of the Museum, and in some cases, as with the Indian Arts and Crafts Board, as a continuation of responsibilities and connections made before his association with MoMA. In many cases, d'Harnoncourt was a director or member of the Board of Trustees of these other organizations. Included in the series is d'Harnoncourt correspondence with the American Association of Museums, the American Council of Learned Societies, the American Craftsmans Council, the American Federation of Arts, the Association of Art Museum Directors, the Brearley School (which was attended by his daughter, Anne), the Center for Inter-American Relations, the Century Club, the Council on Foreign Relations, the Association of American Indian Affairs, the Indian Arts and Crafts Board, the Municipal Art Society, the Museum of Primitive Art, the Museum Council of New York City, the National Book Committee, the National Council on the Arts, the New York State Association of Museums, the New York Worlds Fair 1964-65 Corporation, UNESCO and the International Concil of Museums (ICOM), the United States Air Force Academy, and the John Hay Whitney Foundation.
  - Academy of American Poets, 1963; Brief correspondence and information about the Academy of American Poets, of which RDH agreed to be listed as a sponsor. (Folder VII.1)
  - Albany - Project for the South Mall, 1965-68; Correspondence; photographs. (Folder VII.2)
  - American Association of Museums, 1960-64; Correspondence, reports, information on meetings of the Association. Article by Emily C. Stone, Director of Membership, on the Museums 30th Anniversary Fund Drive in the June 1963 issue of Museum News, the Associations journal. (Folder VII.3)
  - American Association of Museums, 1958-59; Correspondence, reports, information on meetings of the Association. (Folder VII.4)
  - American Association of Museums, 1956-57; Correspondence, reports, information on meetings of the Association. (Folder VII.5)
  - American Association of Museums, 1950-51; Correspondence, reports, information on meetings of the Association. (Folder VII.6)